Guide to the Thomas Sewall Adams Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Sewall Adams papers
1900-1936
MS 31
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.42
(23 boxes)
The papers, relating almost exclusively to matters of taxation, consist of material collected and written for a survey for the American Gas Association; material for a survey of the cement industry in the case United States v. Atlas Portland Cement Company, et al.; material concerning the Committee on Double Taxation of the International Chamber of Commerce and of the League of Nations; papers relating to the Wisconsin Tax Commission; papers relating to the President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership; and papers on state and federal tax problems. The papers contain no personal correspondence and are of interest mainly for specific subjects.
Adams, Thomas Sewall, 1873-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Thomas S. Adams, 1937.
Scope and Contents
The papers, relating almost exclusively to matters of taxation, consist of material collected and written for a survey for the American Gas Association; material for a survey of the cement industry in the case U. S. vs. Atlas Portland Cement Company, et al.; material concerning the Committee on Double Taxation of the International Chamber of Commerce and of the League of Nations; papers relating to the Wisconsin Tax Commission; papers relating to the President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership; and papers on state and federal tax problems. The papers contain no personal correspondence and are of interest mainly for specific subjects.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Sewall Adams was a professor of Political Economy at Yale University, advisor to the United States Treasury Department, and member of the fiscal committee, League of Nations.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged under fourteen headings: Amendments to the revenue bill of 1918, Financial aspects of World War I, American Gas Association survey, Cement survey, International Chamber of Commerce, League of Nations, President's conference on home building and home ownership, United States v. Sugar Institute, Inc., Wisconsin Tax Commission, Miscellaneous papers on taxation, Notebooks, Notecard, Bibliography, and Oversize material.
Business; Cement industries; Economics; Gas industry; Law; Sugar laws and legislation; Taxation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Economists; Educators; Adams, Thomas Sewall, 1873-1933; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Amendments to the revenue bill of 1918
    General note
    Proposed amendments, chiefly by Thomas Sewall Adams in his capacity as economic adviser to the United States Treasury.
    Arrangement
    Arranged by section or titles.
    - Amendments pertaining to the income tax, arranged by sections, 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Amendments to Title V, transportation and insurance, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amendments to Titles II, IV-VI, VIII-XIII, Circa 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Amendments to Title XI, stamp tax, Circa 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Amendments to Title IX, excise tax, Circa 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Amendments to Title X, capital stock tax - insurance companies, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Amendments to Title III, war excess profits tax, 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial aspects of World War I
    - Newspaper clippings on war debts, etc., 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Tables on controlled commodity prices, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The fundamentals of war finance," probably by T. S. Adams, 1917 July (46 pages); "War and national savings, a study in the supply of capital," by David Friday, 1918 March (20 pages), 1917, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Gas Association survey
    Letters and papers relating to a survey made by Thomas Sewall Adams for the American Gas Association to determine the tax burdens upon other classes of public utilities and upon industrial and commercial corporations. This material consists of correspondence, 1926-1927, mainly between H.W. Hartman, assistant manager of the Association, and Benjamin P. Whitaker, assistant to T.S. Adams in the survey, and of statistical data, dating at least as early as 1912, collected by Adams and his staff in 1926-1927. The "General Plan" filed in the first folder, indicated a geographical approach by states, and this plan has been followed in the arrangement of the papers. Material for many states was either not obtained or is not now in the papers, but it is extensive for California, Connecticut, Iowa, Illinois, Indiana, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, Minnesota, Missouri, New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, and Wisconsin, with a great deal less for Florida, Georgia, Maine, Texas, and Virginia. This consists mainly of returned questionnaires and of balance sheets and statements of earnings, 1912, 1922-1925. The State by State data are tabulated on a national basis, according to industries, in a series of 29 charts filed under Tabulation for the United States. Mr. Adams' bibliography is recorded in two small bundles of notes stapled in cardboard covers (filed in box 2).
    - Plan for survey; drafts of survey reports, 1912-1925 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Questionnaires, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Adams' bibliography, Circa 1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous data, 1912-1927 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - California, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Connecticut, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Illinois, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Indiana, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Iowa, 1912-1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Maryland, 1912-1927 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Massachusetts, 1912-1927 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Michigan, 1912-1927 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Minnesota, 1912-1927 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Missouri, 1912-1927 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - New Jersey, 1912-1927 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - New York, 1912-1927 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Pennsylvania, 1912-1927 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Rhode Island, 1912-1927 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Wisconsin, 1912-1927 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - United Gas Improvement Company: subsidiaries in eleven states, 1912-1927 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Tabulation for the United States, 1912-1927 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Cement survey
    Letters, government and private reports, pamphlets, and clippings dealing with a survey of the cement industry made by Thomas Sewall Adams for the years 1921-1928. Included are papers concerning the case of the United States v. Atlas Portland Cement Company, et. al., 1923-1925 in which Adams was a leading witness for the defense; production costs, prices, import charges, etc. 1925-1926, in the cement industry of Belgium; bulletins of the Cement Information Bureau and of the Federal Trade Commission; Department of Commerce bulletins on the cement industry in Belgium, Denmark, England, Germany and Italy; special report on the importation of cements into the United States; income tax returns, 1922-1928, for the following cement companies: Hercules, North American, Glen Falls Portland, Vulcanite Portland, Florida Portland, Signal Mountain Portland, Hermitage Portland, Alpha Portland, Atlas Portland, Southern States Portland, Giant Portland, Pennsylvania-Dixie, International, and Copley.
    - Plan for assembling material for report; correspondence, 1922-1924, 1922-1926 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1925-1929 (Box 5, Folder 5-8)
    - Portland cement industry, confidential form reports, 1926-1928 (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
    - Portland cement industry, confidential form reports, 1926-1928 (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
    - Papers on law case of United States v. Atlas Portland Cement Company, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Monthly cement bulletins of United States Department of Commerce, 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Data on industry in Belgium, 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Special report on imports of foreign cements into the United States, 1878-1924, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Final report of Adams to Cement Information Bureau; paper on trade associations, 1927-1928, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Statistical data on Lehigh Portland Cement Company, 1918-1927 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Printed matter relevant to cement industry, 1917-1927 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Loose notes on cement production, 1900-1928 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - International Chamber of Commerce
    Committee on Double Taxation Correspondence, reports, etc., 1921-1927, concerning the work of the Committee on Double Taxation, with special reference to the American section of this committee of which Thomas Sewall Adams was chairman. Included in the material are transcripts of discussions at international conferences of the Committee, and data on the Geneva Conference on Double Taxation, May 1926, sponsored by the League of Nations.
    See also: League of Nations: Committee on Double Taxation.
    - Correspondence and reports of the Committee on Double Taxation, 1921-1927 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    - Copy of The Record, 1922-07 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Oral report on French taxation, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - League of Nations
    Committee on Double Taxation and Tax Evasion. Typewritten and mimeographed reports, in French and English, 1923-1928, of the committee of experts on double taxation and tax evasion, of which Thomas Sewall Adams was the American representative. Included also are one folder of correspondence, 1922, 1927; a printed report by Sir Arthur Salter on the financial reconstruction of Austria and Hungary, undated and a printed report on double taxation, April. 5, 1923, by Professors, Einaudi, Seligman, and Sir Josiah Stamp.
    - Correspondence, 1922, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Printed Report on Double Taxation submitted to the financial committee by various professors, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Reports on double taxation, 1923-1927 (Box 9, Folder 3-8)
    - Reports on double taxation, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 1-8)
    - Reports on double taxation, 1928, undated (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Printed report by Sir Arthur Slater, "The Financial Reconstruction of Austria and Hungary" (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - President's conference on home building and home ownership
    Letters and papers, 1931-1932, relating to activities of the Committee on taxation, of which Thomas Sewall Adams was chairman. Included are correspondence, 1931-1932; preliminary data; minutes of committee meetings, reports, etc., 1931; and papers by the following: Philip H. Cornick, Harley L. Lutz, Ruth Gillette Hutchinson, Marion K. Mckay, Mabel Newcomer, A.W. Shelton, Herbert D. Simpson, and Rolland A. Vandegrift.
    - Preliminary data, minutes, and various reports, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Reports and minutes of meeting of committee on taxation, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Papers by various persons, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 8-14)
    - Correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
  - United States v. The Sugar Institute, Inc.
    Papers, 1932, concerning the case of U.S. vs. Sugar Institute, including the defense statement, testimony of Thomas Sewall Adams, Evan T. Fisher, and Martin E. Goetzinger; also includes data assembled for the defense.
    - General questions and suggestions by Adams; statistical data, 1911-1931 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Survey of profits of companies selling food products, sugar producing and refining, tobacco and tobacco products, 1925-1931 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Statements of capital employed and profits earned by various refining companies, 1925-1931 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Reports on freight absorptions in the sugar refining industry, 1926-1932 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Tables, graphs, and statistical data, Circa 1925-1936 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Defense statement from trial; two pamphlets dealing with information presented at trial, Circa 1932-1936 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Testimony of T. S. Adams, E. T. Fisher, M. E. Goetzinger, Circa 1932-1936 (Box 13, Folder 3-5)
  - Wisconsin Tax Commission
    Letters and papers dealing with the activities of the Wisconsin Tax Commission, 1905-1927; during part of this time, Thomas Sewall Adams was expert adviser to the Commission.
    Included are assessment studies, 1905-1907; railroad revenues and expenses, 1913-1915, with a paper by James E. Allison on "The depreciation problem in valuation for rate-making"; audit report of the State Tax Commission on the Palmolive Company (subsidiary of Palmolive-Peet Corporation), 1920-1926; and a memorandum on Wisconsin taxes by a member of the Company, 1928. Also includes, papers and letters of the committee on taxation of mine and mineral lands, 1913.
    - Wisconsin Income Tax Act, 1923; two loose pages from The Corporation Journal (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Assessment studies, 1905-1907 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Railroad revenues, 1911-1915 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and audit report on Palmolive-Peet Corp., 1920-1927 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Paper by A. E. Holcomb, "The constitutionality of a state income tax", 1927 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Paper by James E. Allison, "The depreciation problem in valuation for rate-making", 1914 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous papers on taxation, 1900-1933
    Most of these papers concern federal and state fiscal and revenue problems. There is a whole series of correspondence and printed material on federal tax reform, 1918-1928. This includes an interpretation of the 1918 revenue bill, a memorandum on reserves (1919), a questionnaire on federal taxation (1919) and a paper by T.C. Jen on Double Taxation (1924).
    Material on transportation taxes includes papers dealing with railway and auto taxation, 1909-1924, and several letters and memoranda on highway transportation, 1924.
    The problem of state tax commissions appears in the years 1906 and 1916 and there is included here a Summarication of Reports of Tax Commissioners of the Several States. 1906.
    There is correspondence covering two cases which were prosecuted by the United States Board of Tax Appeals in 1930 and much material on the National Tax Association during the whole period. A paper on Pyramiding by Meyer Rothschild, (19 December 1932) was sponsored by this Association. During the years 1912-1916, there was an investigation by a committee of the Association into methods of determining the proportions of interstate properties assignable to each of the several states. This correspondence includes letters to the Wisconsin Committee from several railroads, disclosing the methods of allocation of operating revenues and expenses.
    In 1927 Adams spent considerable time investigating inheritance and estate taxes. In the correspondence for this year are digests of state laws on the subject and a proposal by Adams for modification of the federal estate tax.
    There is much data on mine taxation, 1907-1926. This includes reports of the mine taxation committees in Minnesota, Arizona, Michigan and Wisconsin, 1920-1921, and material on a meeting of the Mining and Metallurgical Society of America, 24 March 1921.
    A considerable number of papers deal with assessment studies. One done in Wisconsin in 1907 contains data on real estate values and assessments of Chicago, Saint Paul, Minneapolis. This is also material on municipal taxation in Winnepeg, Canada, 1921-1924.
    Material on forest taxation includes joint reports by E.S. Allen and Fred R. Fairchild, 1913 on Immature Forests, Proposed Plan for Taxing Virgin Timber, and Outline of a Plan of Forest Taxation for New England.
    A large part of this grouping consists of papers on various aspects of taxation by students and associates of Adams. These include: The Alcabala in Spain, by Professor Norman S. Buck, 1920; The Root of Monopoly is Plain Selfishness, by Professor F.A. Fetter, 1925; The Failure of the Income Tax, by George E. Holmes, 1926; The Development of Franchise Taxation, by Julius O. Roehl, 1906; The French Tax System by Professor Germain Martin, May 1925; Taxation of Life Insurance Companies and Taxation of Life Insurance Companies with Special Reference to Wisconsin, by A.T. Twesme, 1908; The Plan of Utility vs. the Somers System of Taxation, by Napoleon Wagner, 1915; and The Japanese Income Tax, by Y. Yashida, 1908.
    - 1900-1910 (Box 14, Folder 5-10)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1913-1919 (Box 15, Folder 1-10)
    - 1920-1923 (Box 16, Folder 1-11)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
    - 1925-1927 (Box 18, Folder 1-10)
    - 1927-1931 (Box 19, Folder 1-8)
    - 1932-1933, undated (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
  - Notebooks
    - Property tax assessment notebook (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Scope and Contents
      The notebook contains limited writing.
  - Notecards
    - Notes on trade practices, federal income, tax, etc. (Box 20, Folder 8-9)
    - Notes on trade practices, federal income, tax, etc., 1922, undated (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Bibliography
    - Single bibliography arranged on file cards. (Box 22)
  - Oversize material
    - Cement survey
      - Lehigh Portland Cement Company subsidiary company corporation income tax returns, 1922-1928 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Lehigh Portland Cement Company and subsidiary companies corporation income and profits tax returns, 1922-1928 (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
      - Lehigh Portland Cement Company statement of earnings, total assets charts, profit and loss statement; Belgian mill ocean freight price charts, 1922-1928 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Supplementary statistical tables, payroll data, 1922-1928, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Articles on cement; "Portland Cement Plants of the United States" map; cement plant shipment statistics, 1922-1923, 1928, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Article, "Wage Earners Participate in National Prosperity", Circa 1929 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Charts containing taxation data on the United States as a whole, 1915 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - "Comparative condensed tables" for railroads and utilities, 1921-1924 (Box 23, Folder 9)